<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- This is a WordPress eXtended RSS file generated by WordPress as an export of your site. -->
<!-- It contains information about your site's posts, pages, comments, categories, and other content. -->
<!-- You may use this file to transfer that content from one site to another. -->
<!-- This file is not intended to serve as a complete backup of your site. -->

<!-- To import this information into a WordPress site follow these steps: -->
<!-- 1. Log in to that site as an administrator. -->
<!-- 2. Go to Tools: Import in the WordPress admin panel. -->
<!-- 3. Install the "WordPress" importer from the list. -->
<!-- 4. Activate & Run Importer. -->
<!-- 5. Upload this file using the form provided on that page. -->
<!-- 6. You will first be asked to map the authors in this export file to users -->
<!--    on the site. For each author, you may choose to map to an -->
<!--    existing user on the site or to create a new user. -->
<!-- 7. WordPress will then import each of the posts, pages, comments, categories, etc. -->
<!--    contained in this file into your site. -->

	<!-- generator="WordPress/5.9.1" created="2022-03-08 12:18" -->
<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:excerpt="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/excerpt/"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/"
>

<channel>
	<title>TechGeekBuzz</title>
	<link>https://www.techgeekbuzz.com</link>
	<description>Techies World for Tech Geeks</description>
	<pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 12:18:57 +0000</pubDate>
	<language>en-GB</language>
	<wp:wxr_version>1.2</wp:wxr_version>
	<wp:base_site_url>https://www.techgeekbuzz.com</wp:base_site_url>
	<wp:base_blog_url>https://www.techgeekbuzz.com</wp:base_blog_url>

		<wp:author><wp:author_id>28</wp:author_id><wp:author_login><![CDATA[pankajbhadwal]]></wp:author_login><wp:author_email><![CDATA[pankaj@techatom.org]]></wp:author_email><wp:author_display_name><![CDATA[Pankaj Bhadwal]]></wp:author_display_name><wp:author_first_name><![CDATA[Pankaj]]></wp:author_first_name><wp:author_last_name><![CDATA[Bhadwal]]></wp:author_last_name></wp:author>

				
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.9.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/cropped-Techgeekbuzz-Final-Logo-32x32.jpeg</url>
	<title>TechGeekBuzz</title>
	<link>https://www.techgeekbuzz.com</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 

		<item>
		<title><![CDATA[Debian vs CentOS: History Features and Advantages]]></title>
		<link>https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/debian-vs-centos/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2022 08:22:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pankajbhadwal]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/?p=16329</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[With the availability of multiple Linux distributions, choosing the appropriate Linux distribution plays a vital role for any organization. Debian and CentOS are popular and widely used Linux distributions. They are used to handle heavy tasks of development like the hosting of servers. Debian is one of the oldest distributions of Linux Kernel, launched in 1993, while CentOS was released in 2004. Although both distributions have quite a lot of things in common, there exist a few major differences as well.

In this article, we will go through a few of the major differences between the two distributions. Also, we shall discuss what are Debian and CentOS, along with their features, upsides, and downsides.

So, let us get started!
<h2><strong>Package Management</strong></h2>
Packages are included with every operating system. Packages include source code, scripts to run them, manifests, readme files, and so on. To clarify, in the case of Windows, packages are bundled together to form the installer for a certain Application Software, with or without its dependencies.

CentOS as well as Debian both offer efficient package management support with dependency checking features.
<h2><strong>What is Debian?</strong></h2>
The Debian operating system, also known as Debian GNU/Linux, is based on the GNU/Linux operating system. It was one of the first Linux distributions and is still widely used today. It has provided a foundation for many other distributions, including Ubuntu, Mint, Kali, and others.

For application installation, Debian uses the apt-get or aptitude package managers. It is frequently employed as a server or workstation operating system.

The Debian distribution typically has a two-year release cycle. Debian LTS is supported by a distinct group of persons from the Debian project. Debian accounts for around 7% of the market. Debian's regular releases assist users in getting rid of problems as quickly as possible.
<h4>History</h4>
Ian Murdock, in August 1993, first introduced Debian and called it "the Debian Linux Release". He derived this word from Debian by combining the name of his then-girlfriend (ex-wife), Debra Lynn, and his first name. Before Debian, there was a popular Linux distribution, Softlanding Linux System (SLS). However, the poor maintenance and prevalence of buses inspired Murdock to develop new Linux distribution.

Version 0.90 was the first public release of Debian. From 1994 to 1995, the Debian project released the Debian 0.9x versions. Later, in 1996, Debian 1.1 came into existence with many advanced features. The year 1998 witnessed the release of Debian 1.2 and Debian 2.0.

Thereafter, many versions of Debian were released with improvised features. The most recent stable version of the Debian distribution is Debian 11 (bullseye), which was released in 2021.
<h4><strong>Features of Debian</strong></h4>
The following are the features of Debian:
<ul>
 	<li>Open Source</li>
 	<li>Security, Privacy and multiple Identities Management</li>
 	<li>Free to use, and we can contribute to the source code</li>
 	<li>Community support</li>
 	<li>Debian supports desktop environments like XFCE, GNOME, KDE, MATE, Cinnamon, LXDE, and LXQT.</li>
 	<li>Supported CPU architectures are 64 bit Intel and AMD, Intel x86, AMD, IBM Power Systems.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Advantages of Debian</strong></h4>
Here are the significant advantages of Debian:
<ul>
 	<li>Multiple CPU architecture support</li>
 	<li>Configurable</li>
 	<li>Good for administrative tasks</li>
 	<li>A large number of installed packages</li>
 	<li>Multiple Desktop Environments</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Disadvantages of Debian</strong></h4>
The following are the disadvantages of Debian:
<ul>
 	<li>Not user-friendly</li>
 	<li>It does not have a Personal Package Archive (PPA)</li>
</ul>
<h4>When to Choose Debian?</h4>
If you have hands-on experience working with <a href="https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/linux-distros/">Linux distros</a> that use DEB packages, you can choose Debian over CentOS.
<h2><strong>What is CentOS</strong></h2>
CentOS Linux is a community-driven project formed from the roots of Red Hat Enterprise Linux that is stable, predictable, controllable, and repeatable. Many firms also use it for development and production servers.

The first CentOS release, CentOS version 2, in May 2004, was a clone of RHEL version 2.1AS. It has a market share of around 17% amongst companies which is pretty higher than Debian. The release cycle of CentOS is pretty long, which makes the developers face issues as the next update is not going to come sooner. Novices or businessmen heavily leverage CentOS that do not need many administrative tasks.
<h4>History</h4>
The CentOS Linux distribution was introduced as a build of the CAOS Linux. Gregory Kurtzer, in 2002, started CAOS Linux, which is an RPM-based Linux distribution. In 2004, the first version of CentOS as CentOS version 2 was released. It was a fork of an RHEL version 2.1AS.

Many versions of CentOS were released later. Till version 8, CentOS supports x86-64, ARM64, and POWER8 architectures and till version 6. it supported IA-32 architectures. The latest and stable version of CentOS is version 8.0.
<h4><strong>Features of CentOS</strong></h4>
Let us discuss some salient features of CentOS below.
<ul>
 	<li>Free and Open Source</li>
 	<li>Security and Privacy</li>
 	<li>Easy to learn for beginners</li>
 	<li>Installed programming and languages like PHP, Ruby, Perl</li>
 	<li>Supported CPU architectures include IBM Z, AMD, Intel 64 bit, and IBM Power Systems.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Advantages of CentOS</strong></h4>
The following are the remarkable benefits of CentOS:
<ul>
 	<li>Multiple CPU architectures</li>
 	<li>Configurable</li>
 	<li>User-friendly</li>
 	<li>It is very stable</li>
 	<li>Multiple Desktop Support</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Disadvantages of CentOS</strong></h4>
Some major drawbacks of CentOS are as follows:
<ul>
 	<li>The release cycle is pretty high</li>
 	<li>GUI is not interactive</li>
</ul>
<h4>When to Choose CentOS?</h4>
If you want a more stable and secure distro of Linux, choosing CentOS over Debian is a wise choice. Also, learning CentOS is easier than Debian for beginners.
<h2><strong>Differences between the two based on various parameters</strong></h2>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>Features</strong></td>
<td><strong>Debian </strong></td>
<td><strong>CentOS</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<h3><strong>Market and Community</strong></h3>
</td>
<td>Experienced developers who wish to work as administrators choose Debian OS. A businessperson, on the other hand, chooses CentOS if they need a robust and secure Linux distribution for their applications.</td>
<td>Mission-critical and heavy servers are preferred on CentOs as compared to Debian OS. This is why CentOS has a larger market as compared to Debian. The community of CentOS is also greater as compared to Debian.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<h3><strong>Support</strong></h3>
</td>
<td>Debian LTS is supported by a group of separate individuals.</td>
<td>CentOS Project is indirectly supported by the Red Hat Enterprise through third parties like OpenLogic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<h3><strong>Architecture</strong></h3>
</td>
<td>Debian OS will have the support of architectures like MIPSel, MIPS64el, s390x, x86_64/AMD64, and AArch64/ARM64, armhf/armhfp, i386, and ppc64el/ppc64le</td>
<td>CentOS has the support for x86_64/AMD64, AArch64/ARM64, armhf/armhfp, i386, and ppc64el/ppc64le</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<h3><strong>Package Management</strong></h3>
</td>
<td>The package format supported in Debian is DEB, and its package manager is dpkg/APT.

Debian has a relatively large number of packages available with the number exceeding 59000.</td>
<td>The package format supported in CentOS is RPM, and its package manager is YUM/DNF.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<h3><strong>Filesystems</strong></h3>
</td>
<td>Debian supports the ZFS filesystem through the “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dynamic_Kernel_Module_Support" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Dynamic Kernel Module Support</a>” (DKMS) package.</td>
<td>CentOS does not officially support DKMS.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<h3><strong>Release Cycle</strong></h3>
</td>
<td>The release cycle of Debian is around two years. You will stay more updated with new technology with Debian distribution as compared to CentOS.</td>
<td>The release cycle of CentOS is around 4-5 years. Therefore, working with CentOS sometimes creates issues due to bugs as the next major release takes more time.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<h3><strong>Requirements</strong></h3>
</td>
<td>Debian supports 32-bit processors, and the RAM required is 1.5 GB.</td>
<td>CentOS does not support 32-bit processors. The minimum RAM requirement for CentOS is 1.5 GB</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2>Debian vs CentOS - Which is Better?</h2>
Debian and CentOS both are widespread Linux distributions. The choice between Debian and CentOS comes depends on technical requirements, support options, internal resources, and business decisions.

Choosing CentOS would be an excellent move if you run most of your applications on an RHEL-compatible distribution. On the flip side, if you have experience working with the Linux distributions that include DEB packages, Debian is an ideal option.

Therefore, both Debian and CentOS are popular. The choice entirely depends on users and their requirements.
<h2><b>Conclusion</b></h2>
In this article, we saw significant differences between CentOS and Debian. Both are excellent distributions of Linux and thousands and millions of people across the globe use them. CentOS provides more challenges for beginners and is ideal for professionals, but it beats Debian in mission-critical tasks. If you want to select between the two, you can keep the above points in mind and choose the one that best fits your use case.

<strong>People are also reading: </strong>
<ul>
 	<li><a href="https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/ubuntu-vs-centos/">Ubuntu vs CentOS</a></li>
 	<li><a title="Permalink to What is Ubuntu?" href="https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/what-is-ubuntu/" rel="bookmark">What is Ubuntu?</a></li>
 	<li><a title="Permalink to Fedora vs Ubuntu: A Comprehensive Comparison" href="https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/fedora-vs-ubuntu/" rel="bookmark">Fedora vs Ubuntu</a></li>
 	<li><a title="Permalink to What is Debian?" href="https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/what-is-debian/" rel="bookmark">What is Debian?</a></li>
 	<li><a title="Permalink to 10 Best Online Linux Terminals to Use in 2022" href="https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/best-online-linux-terminals/" rel="bookmark">Best Online Linux Terminals</a></li>
 	<li><a title="Permalink to Best Linux Distros to Use in 2022" href="https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/linux-distros/" rel="bookmark">Best Linux Distros</a></li>
 	<li><a title="Permalink to Unix vs Linux: Difference Between Linux and Unix" href="https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/unix-vs-linux/" rel="bookmark">Unix vs Linux</a></li>
 	<li><a title="Permalink to Linux Architecture &amp; It’s Component" href="https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/linux-architecture/" rel="bookmark">Linux Architecture</a></li>
 	<li><a title="Permalink to Linux Cheat Sheet: Download PDF for Quick Reference" href="https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/linux-cheat-sheet/" rel="bookmark">Linux Cheat Sheet</a></li>
 	<li><a title="Permalink to Features of Linux" href="https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/features-of-linux/" rel="bookmark">Features of Linux</a></li>
</ul>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>16329</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2022-03-02 08:22:08]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2022-03-02 08:22:08]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:post_modified><![CDATA[2022-03-06 11:49:33]]></wp:post_modified>
		<wp:post_modified_gmt><![CDATA[2022-03-06 11:49:33]]></wp:post_modified_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[debian-vs-centos]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
										<category domain="category" nicename="centos"><![CDATA[CentOS]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="centos"><![CDATA[CentOS]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="debian"><![CDATA[Debian]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="debian"><![CDATA[Debian]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="debian-vs-centos"><![CDATA[Debian vs CentOS]]></category>
						<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_encloseme]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_yoast_wpseo_linkdex]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[67]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_yoast_wpseo_title]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[Debian vs CentOS: History Features and Advantages]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_yoast_wpseo_content_score]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[60]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_yoast_wpseo_estimated-reading-time-minutes]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[6]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_yoast_wpseo_focuskw]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[Debian vs CentOS]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_yoast_wpseo_metadesc]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[Find the best OS between Debian vs CentOS to boost your productivity and scale your skills set, this article will give you detailed brief.]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_yoast_wpseo_primary_category]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2534]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_wp_old_date]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2021-10-11]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							</item>
					<item>
		<title><![CDATA[Ubuntu vs CentOS: History, Features, and Advantages]]></title>
		<link>https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/ubuntu-vs-centos/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2022 09:28:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pankajbhadwal]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/?p=16631</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<span style="font-weight: 400;">Today, Ubuntu and CentOS are popular operating systems. They are used to perform heavy development activities like server hosting, learning, development, and as a home operating system.  Interestingly, they both were released in the year 2004. Although both distributions have many characteristics in common, there are a few key distinctions. </span>

<span style="font-weight: 400;">In this post, we'll look at some of the key distinctions between these two distributions. Before diving into the respective operating systems comparison, let’s see the responsibilities performed by both the Operating Systems.</span>
<h2><b>What are the responsibilities of Ubuntu and CentOS?</b></h2>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">Ubuntu and CentOS, both are Operating Systems. Both of them are responsible for managing computer memory, processes, and the operations of all devices and programs in the machine. The operating system is the most crucial component of your machines that is responsible for the communication between users and hardware.  </span>
<ul>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><b><i>Program Execution</i></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">: They both are in charge of executing all sorts of programs, whether they are a user or system applications.</span></li>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><b><i>Managing Input/Output Operations</i></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">: They both are in charge of handling all types of inputs, such as those from a keyboard, mouse, or desktop.</span></li>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><b><i>Manipulation of the File System</i></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">: They are both in charge of making decisions about the storage of all sorts of data or files, such as floppy disks/hard disks/pen drives, and so on.</span></li>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><b><i>Error Detection and Handling</i></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">: They are both in charge of detecting any sort of error or defect that may arise while doing any operation. In cases of error detection, it may generate some signals or interrupts to stop the processing of a program. This ensures the corrupted task is immediately stopped before affecting other running jobs.</span></li>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><b><i>Resource Allocation</i></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">: The Operating Systems guarantee that all available resources are used properly by determining which resources are to be used by whom and for how long.</span></li>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><b><i>Information and Data Protection</i></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">: They both manage all the users’ data effectively and ensure that it is not accessed without permission.</span></li>
</ul>
<h2><b>What is Ubuntu</b></h2>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">Ubuntu is an open-source Linux system based on Debian that was introduced in 2004. Ubuntu, which is supported by Canonical Ltd., is regarded as an excellent distribution for beginners and is extensively used for educational purposes. The operating system is not often used for demanding activities such as server administration. The term "</span><b>ubuntu</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">" comes from the Zulu language of Africa and means "compassion to others."</span>

<span style="font-weight: 400;">The primary version of Ubuntu makes use of the </span><b><i>GNOME </i></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">environment, which includes a graphical user interface (GUI) and a collection of desktop apps for Linux. GNOME is designed to be comparable to the Windows desktop experience in order to make Linux easier to use for non-programmers. Besides, Ubuntu provides many languages and keyboard configurations which ensures people from every community and region have the right to use it.</span>
<h3>History</h3>
The first release of Ubuntu was in 2004 and its name was Ubuntu 4.10. Every release of Ubuntu has a version number consisting of the year and of the month of release. Ubuntu releases an updated version after every six months, where each version gets free support for nine months.

Furthermore, the current long-term support (TLS) releases are supported for five years and released after every two years. This long-term support (TLS) includes updates for security patches, new hardware, and updates to the 'Ubuntu Stack'. The latest and stable version of Ubuntu is Ubuntu 21.10, released in October 2021.
<h3><b>Features of Ubuntu</b></h3>
Some significant features of Ubuntu are, as listed below:
<h4><strong>Open source and freely available</strong></h4>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">It is an open-source distribution that can be downloaded and configured by any person. Ubuntu was developed on the idea that every person has the equal right to contribute to the source code of it.</span>
<h4><strong>Fully configurable</strong></h4>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">You can modify the distribution according to your use case. This is the major advantage of software being open-source. You can even publish a completely new distribution based on Ubuntu by yourself.</span>
<h4><strong>Desktop Environments</strong></h4>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">Multiple Desktop Environments including </span><b><i>Gnome</i></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">, </span><b><i>KDE</i></b> <b><i>Plasma</i></b><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">, </span></i><b><i>Mate</i></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">, etc. are supported in Ubuntu. Gnome is the default desktop environment that is available when you install the OS.</span>
<h4><strong>Identity and Access Management</strong></h4>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">Multiple users can work on the same operating system without interfering with each other. The root user sets the “read and write” permissions for each user. Each user has their own password and set of resources.</span>
<h4><strong>Multiple Variants</strong></h4>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">Multiple flavors are available like Kubuntu, Lubuntu, Ubuntu Studio, Ubuntu Kylin. Different variants are made for different purposes. For instance, Edubuntu is suited for educational purposes and Xubuntu is suitable when we have limited computational power.</span>
<h4><strong>Multiple CPU architecture Support</strong></h4>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">Ubuntu supports multiple CPU architectures including Intel x86, AMD64, ARM, Power Servers, etc.</span>
<h3>Advantages of Ubuntu</h3>
The following are some notable benefits of Ubuntu:
<ul>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is a user-friendly operating system that is frequently the first Linux distribution downloaded by beginners.</span></li>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">It ensures privacy and security to its users and therefore multiple users can work on the same machine without needing to worry about interference.</span></li>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">We can choose from multiple desktop environments and CPU architectures according to the use case. This feature makes it a widely used OS, not only for home PCs but for other applications like embedded systems as well.</span></li>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">It requires 1.5 GB to 2GB RAM and a minimum of 20-25 GB free storage for its installation which is pretty minimal demand for today’s machines. </span></li>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">It has frequent updates which ensure a bug is resolved quickly.</span></li>
</ul>
<h3><b>Disadvantages of Ubuntu</b></h3>
Here are the significant drawbacks of Ubuntu:
<ul>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Not suitable for high graphics and </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">AAA</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> title games since it’s primarily built for development purposes.</span></li>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Not suitable for mission-critical tasks like servers.</span></li>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Does not come pre-installed on modern machines and we need to explicitly install it via bootable hardware.</span></li>
</ul>
<h3>When to Choose Ubuntu?</h3>
If you are a beginner to Linux operating system, choosing Ubuntu over CentOS would be a great choice.
<h2><b>What is CentOS</b></h2>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">CentOS (</span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">from Community Enterprise Operating System</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">) Linux is a policy formed from the roots of Red Hat Enterprise Linux that is stable, predictable, controllable, and repeatable. Many firms also use it for development and production servers. The first CentOS release, CentOS version 2, in May 2004, was a clone of RHEL version 2.1AS. CentOS version numbers prior to 7.0 include two portions, a major version, and a minor version, which correspond to the main version and update set of Red Hat Enterprise Linux used to produce a unique CentOS release.</span>

<span style="font-weight: 400;">CentOS has less native support for desktop programs like multimedia, such as video and audio editors and renderer tools. Many of these desktop apps may be found in third-party repositories such as </span><b><i>EPEL</i></b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> and </span><b><i>NUX</i></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span>

<span style="font-weight: 400;">CentOS is extremely reliable, with long-term support (at least five years) for each major version, as well as rolling upgrades for minor version updates (i.e., dot-level upgrades).</span>
<h3>History</h3>
The first release of CentOS was in May 2004 as CentOS version 2.0. It was a fork of REHL version 2.1AS. All the releases of CentOS up to version 6 supported the IA-32 architecture and up to version 8, all the releases supported POWER8, ARM64, and x86-64 architectures.

The AltArch releases of CentOS 7 supports the IA-32, Power ISA, and the variants of ARM architecture, ARMv7hl, and AArch64, as of December 2015. The latest and stable version of CentOS is CentOS 8.5.2111, released in November 2021.
<h3><b>Features of CentOS</b></h3>
<h4><strong>Multiple CPU architectures</strong></h4>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">CPU architectures like </span><b><i>IBM</i></b> <b><i>Z</i></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">, </span><b><i>AMD</i></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">, and </span><b><i>Intel 64 bit, IBM Power Systems</i></b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> are supported in CentOS.</span>
<h4><strong>Free and Open Source</strong></h4>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">It is an open-source Operating System that can be used and configured by any person. This ensures that bugs are resolved faster and everyone has the equal right to contribute.</span>
<h4><strong>Suitable for mission-critical tasks</strong></h4>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">It is widely used for heavy-end and mission-critical tasks like hosting servers. It also does not have fancy multimedia support as servers and virtual machines do not need it.</span>
<h4><strong>Package Manager</strong></h4>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">The package manager is </span><b><i>YUM/DNF</i></b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> for installing and managing packages.</span>
<h4><strong>Security for transmission</strong></h4>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">It has support for </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">SSL</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> and </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">TLS </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">to ensure data is transferred securely over the network. This is particularly helpful while connecting to virtual and remote machines.</span>
<h3><b>Advantages of CentOS</b></h3>
<ul>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is a free and Open Source distribution that is available for everyone. A release of CentOS is stable for the next 4-5 years.</span></li>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is suitable for handling heavy loads of servers. This is the reason it is used by many companies as their server OS.</span></li>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">It has multiple Desktop and CPU architecture support that you can use on multiple types of hardware.</span></li>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is less prone to cyber attacks.</span></li>
</ul>
<h3><b>Disadvantages of CentOS</b></h3>
<ul>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is not suitable as an office or home Desktop as there is poor support of multimedia.</span></li>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is not suitable for multimedia and gaming related tasks</span></li>
 	<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">The release cycle is 4-5 years which is a drawback if there is a major bug found in a release.</span></li>
</ul>
<h3>When to Choose CentOS?</h3>
CentOS is ideal to choose when you require a stable and secure operating system for performing administrative tasks.
<h2><b>Descriptive comparison on various features </b></h2>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Package Management</span></h3>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">The package manager used by CentOS is </span><b><i>YUM</i></b> <span style="font-weight: 400;">while that of Ubuntu is </span><b><i>apt-get</i></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span>

<span style="font-weight: 400;">“YUM” is often associated with the RHEL family of operating systems and handles RPM software packages, whereas “apt” is associated with the Debian family of distributions and handles deb software packages.</span>

<span style="font-weight: 400;">Both are used to install, uninstall, and update software packages obtained via software repositories.</span>
<h3><strong>Release Cycle</strong></h3>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">Ubuntu has a 2-year release cycle, whereas CentOS has a 4-5-year cycle. A shorter release cycle is beneficial for problem resolution and remaining updated with technology. A short release cycle, however, results in reduced stability of the operating system because one version does not stay for long. Longer life cycles, on the other hand, ensure the stability of the operating system. However, if a major bug exists in a release, it may take some time to be rectified.</span>
<h3><strong>Community and Market Share</strong></h3>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">Since Ubuntu is widely used by beginners and is used for small-scale applications, it has a comparatively larger community than CentOS. You can find an ample amount of threads and tutorials on Ubuntu. The market share of Ubuntu is around 38% which is comparatively more than CentOS with a 17.5% share of the market.</span>
<h3><strong>Usage</strong></h3>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">Ubuntu is an easy-to-use operating system that is ideal for novices. It features an easy-to-understand GUI, which assures that users coming from GUI-based operating systems such as Windows have little difficulty comprehending the flow. CentOS, on the other hand, is better suited for professionals due to a lack of multimedia and GUI capabilities.</span>
<h3><strong>Variants</strong></h3>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">Ubuntu has variations such as Kubuntu, Lubuntu, Ubuntu Studio, and Ubuntu Kylin that you may choose depending on your needs. When you have a low processing capacity, one of the options is to utilize the Xubuntu version. CentOS, on the other hand, does not give official variations, and you must use the same variant for all use cases.</span>
<h3><strong>Web Hosting and Performance</strong></h3>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">CentOS has cPanel support, which provides a graphical user interface for web hosting. Furthermore, it is more stable since the developers devote more time to delivering the next version of the operating system. However, Ubuntu does not support cPanel (though other options are available), and the versions are not very stable.</span>
<h2><b>Ubuntu vs CentOS - Head-to-Head Comparison</b></h2>
The following table draws all the key differences between Ubuntu and CentOS:
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><b>Features</b></td>
<td><b>CentOS</b></td>
<td><b>Ubuntu</b></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">Base</span></td>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">CentOS is based on Red Hat</span></td>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">Ubuntu is based on Debian</span></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">Release Cycle</span></td>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">Around 4-5 years</span></td>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">Around 2 years</span></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">Package Manager</span></td>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">apt-get</span></td>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">YUM</span></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">Stability</span></td>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">Very stable and reliable for servers</span></td>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">Not highly stable</span></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">Use case</span></td>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">For server management and mission-critical tasks</span></td>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">For learning and small industries</span></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">Virtualization</span></td>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">KVM, Xen</span></td>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">Native KVM support</span></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">Package format</span></td>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">CentOS uses RPM package format</span></td>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">Ubuntu uses DEB package format</span></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">CPU architectures</span></td>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">CentOS supports x86_64/AMD64, AArch64/ARM64, armhf/armhfp, i386, and ppc64el/ppc64le</span></td>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">Ubuntu supports Intel x86, AMD64, ARM, Power Servers, S390X, PowerPC</span></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">Variants</span></td>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">CentOS does not have official variants</span></td>
<td><span style="font-weight: 400;">Ubuntu has many variants including Kubuntu, Lubuntu, and Ubuntu Studio.</span></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2><b>Ubuntu vs CentOS - Which is Better?</b></h2>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">There is no distribution that outperforms its rival in every parameter. In one use scenario, Ubuntu may be superior to CentOS, but in another, CentOS may be superior to Ubuntu. Because of its user-friendly interface, Ubuntu is highly recommended for beginners. It also offers a big community and tutorials to assist newcomers. CentOS, on the other hand, is suggested for administrative duties and servers that require a very stable and secure operating system.</span>
<h2><b>Conclusion</b></h2>
<span style="font-weight: 400;">We discussed significant disparities between CentOS and Ubuntu in this post. Both are great Linux distributions that are used by millions of people across the world. CentOS presents more obstacles for novices and is hence preferred by experts, whereas Ubuntu is better suited for students and home PCs. Both are free open source distributions that you can use based on your needs by examining the factors listed above.</span>

<strong>People are also reading: </strong>
<ul>
 	<li><a title="Permalink to Fedora vs Ubuntu: A Comprehensive Comparison" href="https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/fedora-vs-ubuntu/" rel="bookmark">Fedora vs Ubuntu</a></li>
 	<li><a title="Permalink to What is Ubuntu?" href="https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/what-is-ubuntu/" rel="bookmark">What is Ubuntu?</a></li>
 	<li><a title="Permalink to What is Debian?" href="https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/what-is-debian/" rel="bookmark">What is Debian?</a></li>
 	<li><a title="Permalink to Unix vs Linux: Difference Between Linux and Unix" href="https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/unix-vs-linux/" rel="bookmark">Unix vs Linux</a></li>
 	<li><a title="Permalink to What is Linux Operating System?" href="https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/what-is-linux-operating-system/" rel="bookmark">What is Linux Operating System?</a></li>
 	<li><a href="https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/debian-vs-centos/">Debian vs CentOS</a></li>
 	<li><a title="Permalink to 10 Best Online Linux Terminals to Use in 2022" href="https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/best-online-linux-terminals/" rel="bookmark">Best Online Linux Terminals</a></li>
 	<li><a title="Permalink to How to Learn Linux?" href="https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/how-to-learn-linux/" rel="bookmark">How to Learn Linux?</a></li>
 	<li><a title="Permalink to Best Linux Distros to Use in 2022" href="https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/linux-distros/" rel="bookmark">Best Linux Distros</a></li>
 	<li><a title="Permalink to Best Linux Certifications" href="https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/best-linux-certifications/" rel="bookmark">Best Linux Certifications</a></li>
</ul>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>16631</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2022-03-02 09:28:43]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2022-03-02 09:28:43]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:post_modified><![CDATA[2022-03-06 11:52:11]]></wp:post_modified>
		<wp:post_modified_gmt><![CDATA[2022-03-06 11:52:11]]></wp:post_modified_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[ubuntu-vs-centos]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
										<category domain="category" nicename="centos"><![CDATA[CentOS]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="centos"><![CDATA[CentOS]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="ubuntu"><![CDATA[Ubuntu]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="ubuntu"><![CDATA[Ubuntu]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="ubuntu-vs-centos"><![CDATA[Ubuntu vs CentOS]]></category>
						<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_yoast_wpseo_content_score]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[30]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_yoast_wpseo_estimated-reading-time-minutes]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[10]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_yoast_wpseo_title]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[Ubuntu vs CentOS: History, Features, and Advantages]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_yoast_wpseo_linkdex]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[63]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_yoast_wpseo_primary_category]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2535]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_yoast_wpseo_focuskw]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[Ubuntu vs CentOS]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_yoast_wpseo_metadesc]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[This blog post will help you to identify the best linux distribution between Ubuntu vs CentOS, Also help you with the detailed comparisons.]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_encloseme]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_wp_old_date]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2021-10-17]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							</item>
					<item>
		<title><![CDATA[40 Top Azure Interview Questions and Answers in 2022]]></title>
		<link>https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/top-azure-interview-questions-and-answers/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 04:59:57 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pankajbhadwal]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/?p=22512</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Microsoft Azure or Azure is a cloud computing platform managed by Microsoft. It is among the leading cloud computing services available currently in the market. The increasing trend of businesses moving to the cloud has increased the demand for cloud services dramatically. As a result, cloud computing services providers like Azure have become quite popular.

Today, many businesses that use Azure are in constant search of cloud computing experts who are well aware of the services offered by Azure. Also, a cloud computing expert is expected to figure out all the requirements of a business and suggest the cloud computing services required to run business operations efficiently.

If you are interested in building a career in the tech industry as a cloud expert, you can aim for working with a leading cloud service provider like Azure. However, you need to prepare yourself effectively to improve your chances of cracking an interview. One good way to prepare for the Azure interview is to go through the most frequently asked Azure interview questions.

Well, this article intends to make you familiar with the Azure interview questions that are the favorites of interviewers. Also, we will provide an appropriate answer to each question so that you make the most of your time reading this article.
<h2><strong>List of 40 Top Azure Interview Questions and Answers</strong></h2>
The Azure interview questions that we have listed below are divided into three categories - basic, intermediate, and advanced. Let’s start with the basic Azure interview questions.
<h3><strong>Basic Azure Interview Questions</strong></h3>
<h4><strong>1. What is cloud computing?</strong></h4>
Cloud computing refers to the delivery of IT resources or computing services over the internet. The resources that one can get with cloud computing include servers, networking, software, and storage.

In general, cloud computing services follow the pay-as-you-go pricing model, which means that users only pay for the resources that they use. The reason behind the widespread popularity of cloud computing is that it helps businesses to cut the costs and efforts required to manage their own IT infrastructure.
<h4><strong>2. What are the various cloud deployment models?</strong></h4>
There are three main cloud deployment models, namely public cloud, private cloud, and hybrid cloud.

<b>1) Public Cloud - </b>In the public cloud deployment model, the cloud services are delivered over the public internet. Also, the cloud service provider has complete control over the cloud infrastructure and the resources are shared among different users.

The public cloud is usually cost-effective but the security concerns associated with it are high as it allows multiple users to share applications, storage, and other computing resources.

<b>2) Private Cloud - </b>When it comes to the private cloud model, a single organization or business owns the cloud infrastructure and uses all its resources. Also, the organization has the choice to either manage the cloud infrastructure by themselves or by a third party.

As all the resources are available exclusively for a single organization, the costs associated with a private cloud are higher compared to the public cloud. However, the public cloud is safe and secure as the access to resources is limited to only a single entity.

<b>3) Hybrid Cloud - </b>The hybrid cloud model is a combination of public cloud and private cloud. An organization can use both public and private cloud simultaneously while the computing services are offered by different providers.

One typical instance of a hybrid cloud is when an organization makes use of a private cloud to store their confidential data but uses a public cloud to host one of their web applications accessible to the general public.
<h4><strong>3. What are the different cloud service models? Give a brief description of each model.</strong></h4>
Cloud providers usually offer their services in three different services models - IaaS (Infrastructure-as-a-Service), PaaS (Platform-as-a-Service), and SaaS (Software-as-a-Service).
<ol>
 	<li><b> IaaS - </b>IaaS or Infrastructure-as-a-Service refers to the cloud services offered at the infrastructural level, such as physical computing resources or hardware, virtual machines, etc. For instance, you can get a server that you can configure as per your requirements with access to its underlying operating system and other networking capabilities.</li>
 	<li><b> PaaS - </b>PaaS or Platform-as-a-Service is the cloud service model that allows the delivery of services required by users to develop and deploy applications. One significant characteristic of PaaS is that it does not give users access to the underlying hardware, servers, storage, etc. of the platform. Users are simply provided with the development environment that they can configure to develop and deploy their applications effectively.</li>
 	<li><b> SaaS - </b>SaaS or Software-as-a-Service is the cloud service model that allows users to access software or applications hosted on a cloud infrastructure. While users can access the features offered by a cloud-hosted application, they do not have access to the application data and the cloud infrastructure used to host the application.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>4. What is Microsoft Azure and what services does it offer?</strong></h4>
Azure is a cloud computing platform that offers a wide range of cloud services under IaaS, PaaS, and SaaS models. Microsoft developed the Azure platform and it was made available for public use in October 2008.

The cloud computing services offered by Azure are quite vast with the main categories being as follows:
<ul>
 	<li>AI &amp; Machine Learning</li>
 	<li>Compute</li>
 	<li>Containers</li>
 	<li>Database</li>
 	<li>Developer Tools</li>
 	<li>IoT</li>
 	<li>Media</li>
 	<li>Networking</li>
 	<li>Security</li>
 	<li>Storage</li>
 	<li>Web</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>5. Is Azure different from Amazon AWS and GCP?</strong></h4>
While Microsoft Azure, Amazon AWS, and GCP (Google Cloud Platform) are all cloud computing platforms, the services offered by them differ from one another.

Apart from being highly popular among enterprises, these three are the leading cloud providers in terms of market share. Thus, <a href="https://www.techgeekbuzz.com/google-cloud-vs-aws-vs-azure-cloud-platform-you-should-look-for/">Google Cloud vs AWS vs Azure</a> is one of the most popular debates among cloud computing professionals.
<h4><strong>6. Name some of the most popular Azure products and services.</strong></h4>
Following are the most popular Azure products and services:
<ul>
 	<li>Azure CDN</li>
 	<li>Azure SQL</li>
 	<li>CosmosDB</li>
 	<li>Azure Active Directory</li>
 	<li>Azure Data Factory</li>
 	<li>DevOps</li>
 	<li>Azure Backup</li>
 	<li>Azure Logic Apps</li>
 	<li>API Management</li>
 	<li>Azure Site Recovery</li>
 	<li>Azure Bots</li>
 	<li>Virtual Machines</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>7. What is Azure CDN?</strong></h4>
Azure CDN or Content Delivery Network is a popular service offered by Azure that allows websites, web apps to load quickly, be more responsive, and save bandwidth. It can easily integrate with other Azure services and comes with the ability to handle loads due to unprecedented traffic spikes.

Additionally, Azure CDN offers various features, including developer tools and APIs to build global applications, protection against threats like <a href="https://www.imperva.com/learn/ddos/denial-of-service/">DDoS attacks</a>, and advanced analytics to monitor the traffic and the performance of the content.
<h4><strong>8. Explain the principal components of Microsoft Azure.</strong></h4>
Microsoft Azure has three principal components, namely Compute, Storage, and Fabric.
<ul>
 	<li><b>Azure Compute</b></li>
</ul>
Azure Compute is responsible for providing all the infrastructure that users need to run their applications on the cloud. Users can build applications from scratch or deploy their existing apps with the help of services available under Azure Compute, such as Virtual Machines, Azure Kubernetes Service (AKS), Virtual Machine Scale Sets, and Azure Functions.
<ul>
 	<li><b>Azure Storage</b></li>
</ul>
Azure Storage provides secure, scalable, and cost-effective cloud storage to users. There are various storage services available under Azure Storage, such as Blob Storage, Data Lake Storage, Data Box, and Azure Files.
<ul>
 	<li><b>Azure Fabric</b></li>
</ul>
Azure Fabric acts as a platform that facilitates the development of microservices. It also helps to tackle the challenges associated with the development and management of cloud applications. Azure Fabric supports a wide array of programming languages and models.
<h4><strong>9. What is the Azure storage account key?</strong></h4>
To access an Azure storage account, a user needs to have an account name and a key as credentials. The account key behaves as a password to access the storage account. By using Azure CLI (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Command-line_interface">command-line interface</a>), users can manage their storage account keys with ease.
<h4><strong>10. Can you explain the role of Azure Resource Manager?</strong></h4>
Azure Resource Manager is a service that allows users to manage the resources that they opt for. Also, it provides users with access to a management layer that makes it really simple to add, remove, and update the resources in their accounts. Azure Resource Manager offers various management features, such as access control and tags to organize the deployed resources.
<h4><strong>11. What is Azure Redis Cache?</strong></h4>
The Azure Redis Cache is an in-memory data store offered by Azure. Based on the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Redis">Redis</a> software, Azure Redis Cache helps to improve the performance of web applications. It basically stores the data received from the backend during the very first request.

Later, the data is provided directly from the Redis cache, which boosts the performance of a web application. The best part of Azure Redis Cache is that it supports a wide range of data structures, including strings, bitmaps, hashes, and geospatial indexes.
<h4><strong>12. How autoscaling feature offered by Azure is helpful for users?</strong></h4>
The autoscaling feature offered by Azure helps to automatically increase or decrease the number of resources required to ensure the smooth operation of an application or website.

For instance, if there is a sudden spike in the number of users of an application, the autoscaling feature will automatically increase the number of available resources to meet the demand. Also, as soon as the active user count starts moving back to normal, the extra resources will be discarded.
<h4><strong>13. Explain Table Storage in Microsoft Azure.</strong></h4>
Table Storage is one of the key storage services offered by Microsoft Azure. It allows users to store structured NoSQL data and offers a key-value store. Table Storage has become an ideal choice for applications that require a flexible data schema.
<h4><strong>14. Why do we need the Azure Diagnostics API?</strong></h4>
For applications that run on Azure, it becomes essential for developers to monitor their performance effectively, and the Azure Diagnostics API is exactly what helps to do so. The API collects diagnostic data that helps to create charts for better performance monitoring.
<h3><strong>Intermediate Azure Interview Questions</strong></h3>
<h4><strong>15. Explain Azure virtual machine scale sets?</strong></h4>
Azure virtual machine scale sets are computation resources that allow users to deploy as well as manage the sets of similar virtual machines (VMs). These scale sets to support autoscaling of applications as they are configured similarly. Also, they eliminate the need for pre-provisioning the VMs.

By leveraging Azure virtual machine sets, it becomes easier to develop complex applications that work with big data and containerized workloads.
<h4><strong>16. What is CSPack in Azure?</strong></h4>
CSPack is basically a command-line tool that helps users to prepare their applications for deployment in Azure. The tool generates the service package files having the .cscfg extension. The service package file allows users to configure the cloud service.

The file contains information about the number of instances required to deploy for every existing role within the service, configuration settings, and certificate thumbprints.
<h4><strong>17. What services allow us to manage Azure resources?</strong></h4>
Azure Resource Manager allows us to manage all the resources that we have opted for. It allows us to use a simple JSON file to manage, deploy as well as delete resources.
<h4><strong>18. Explain Azure Queue Storage along with its key advantages.</strong></h4>
Azure Queue Storage is an Azure service that allows message queuing for huge workloads. It helps to develop applications that are flexible, modular, and durable. Following are the main advantages of using Azure Queue Storage:
<ul>
 	<li>It makes an application easily scalable so that the sudden increase in traffic or users can be handled effectively to prevent server overload.</li>
 	<li>It supports message buffering to prevent the failure of an application in case a part of the application architecture goes down. The buffered messages are automatically forwarded to other message processing nodes to ensure that the application operates normally.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>19. Describe the use of Azure Traffic Manager.</strong></h4>
Being a traffic load Balancer, Azure Traffic Manager is responsible for distributing an application’s traffic across various global Azure regions. The primary objective of Azure Traffic Manager is to ensure optimal performance of an application and minimize the overall downtime.

It makes use of DNS to identify the service endpoint that is best suited for a particular client request. Also, the Traffic Manager constantly monitors the health of endpoints to make sure that the client requests are not directed to an endpoint that is having some issues.
<h4><strong>20. What is the process for setting up an Azure Virtual Machine?</strong></h4>
Setting up a virtual machine in Azure is a straightforward task. You need to have an active Azure account and by following the steps mentioned below, you can create a virtual machine:
<ul>
 	<li>Log in to your account on the Azure portal.</li>
 	<li>Click on the “Create a resource” option that is available under “Azure services.”</li>
 	<li>Select either “Windows Server 2019 Datacenter” or “Ubuntu Server 20.04LTS.”</li>
 	<li>Provide all the relevant information required to set up the virtual machine.</li>
 	<li>Choose the size of your virtual machine.</li>
 	<li>Review all the information and click the “Review + create” button.</li>
 	<li>Once the validation process is complete, click the “Create” button.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>21. What is Azure Service Level Agreement (SLA)?</strong></h4>
The Azure Service Level Agreement (SLA) highlights Azure’s commitment related to the uptime and connectivity of its various services. It’s important for every user to know that the Azure SLA has individual commitments for each Azure service.
<h4><strong>22. State the difference between a library and a list.</strong></h4>
<b>Library - </b>A library is an interface that allows us to store and manage documents. Also, the documents can be created using Microsoft Word, Microsoft Excel, and Microsoft Powerpoint.

<b>List - </b>List is also an interface, but it facilitates the representation of items in a table having rows and columns. Also, you can attach lists with documents.
<h4><strong>23. What is Azure Backup? Explain the different types of replication supported by Azure Backup.</strong></h4>
The Azure Backup is a service that allows users to backup their data securely on the Azure cloud and retrieves it conveniently. Azure Backup uses three types of replication models to ensure instant availability of data:
<ul>
 	<li><b>Locally Redundant Storage (LRS):</b></li>
</ul>
This model creates three copies of the data in the single storage unit of a data center. LRS is an ideal model that allows users to secure data from local hardware failures in a cost-effective way. Also, all the copies are available in the same region as that of the original data.
<ul>
 	<li><b>Geo-redundant storage (GRS):</b></li>
</ul>
The geo-redundant model stores the replicated data in a different region than that of original data. It costs more than LRS but ensures the availability of data even when there is an outage in the region where the original data exists.
<ul>
 	<li><b>Zone-redundant Storage (ZRS):</b></li>
</ul>
In this replication model, the replicated data is available across a number of availability zones that are present in the same region. Also, ZRS has zero downtime.
<h4><strong>24. What is the role of Azure Scheduler?</strong></h4>
Azure Scheduler is a highly useful service that allows users to create and schedule jobs. Also, all the actions associated with a job are executed automatically. With Azure Scheduler, users can define when to run jobs and access the history of job results. It also lets users run a job immediately or schedule it. In all, Azure Schedule makes it possible for users to create and run scheduled jobs.
<h4><strong>25. How would you deploy a SQL database in Azure?</strong></h4>
Following are the steps that allow us to deploy a SQL database in Azure:
<ul>
 	<li>Log in to your account on the Azure portal.</li>
 	<li>Navigate to the “SQL Databases” and then click “Servers.”</li>
 	<li>You need to choose one of the listed servers with which you want to connect.</li>
 	<li>Hit the “Configure” button.</li>
 	<li>Now, you need to open the SQL Server Management Studio.</li>
 	<li>Enter the server name and then switch to the SQL Server and Windows Authentication mode.</li>
 	<li>Enter the username (that you have specified while creating that particular DB server) and the password.</li>
 	<li>Click “Connect.”</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>26. How is the Azure Service Bus Queue different from the Azure Storage Queue?</strong></h4>
Azure Service Bus Queue and Azure Storage Queue are the two types of queues offered by Azure. Here are the key differences between the Azure Service Bus Queue and Azure Storage Queue:
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><b>Service Bus Queue</b></td>
<td><b>Storage Queue</b></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Service Bus Queue is a part of Azure messaging infrastructure.</td>
<td>Storage Queue is a part of the Azure Storage infrastructure.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>It guarantees FIFO (first-in-first-out) delivery.</td>
<td>It does not guarantee FIFO delivery.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Service Bus Queue supports the duplicate detection feature that can be configured on the sender side.</td>
<td>No duplicate detection feature is available in Storage Queue.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>It does not offer a server-side transaction log.</td>
<td>It offers a server-side transaction log.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The maximum queue size is 80GB.</td>
<td>The maximum queue size is 500TB.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>It supports 10,000 queues per service namespace.</td>
<td>It supports an unlimited number of queues.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h4><strong>27. Describe enterprise data warehouse.</strong></h4>
Enterprise data warehouse allows users to bring all their data in a common space where it can be analyzed and processed to get meaningful insights.

Enterprise data warehouse with Azure makes it possible for users or businesses to get insights through modern and interactive analytics dashboards and detailed operational reports. Following are the key components required to create an enterprise data warehouse with Azure:
<ul>
 	<li>Azure Synapse Analytics</li>
 	<li>Azure Blob Storage</li>
 	<li>Synapse Pipelines Documentation</li>
 	<li>Azure Synapse Analytics Spark pools</li>
 	<li>Azure Analysis Services</li>
 	<li>Power BI</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>28. What is a role instance in Azure?</strong></h4>
Role instance is simply a virtual machine that runs the application code using the running role configurations. It is worthwhile noting that a single role can have more than one instance and that can be defined within the service configuration file.
<h4><strong>29. What should you do in case of a drive failure?</strong></h4>
Whenever we encounter a drive failure, we need to take the following actions:
<ul>
 	<li>Unmount the drive so that the Azure storage can function without fail.</li>
 	<li>Replace the drive so that it becomes possible to remount and format the affected drive.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>30. Explain Availability Set.</strong></h4>
In Azure, an availability set is a group of virtual machines (VMs) that are configured differently. The virtual machines in the availability set are created using different images and configurations. Availability sets are an ideal choice for applications that have known workload requirements.
<h3><strong>Advanced Azure Interview Questions</strong></h3>
<h4><strong>31. Highlight the key difference between Availability Sets and Scale Sets in Azure.</strong></h4>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><b>Availability Set</b></td>
<td><b>Scale Set</b></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>An availability set is a group of virtual machines that have different configurations.</td>
<td>A scale is a group of virtual machines that have identical configurations.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Virtual machines are created using different images and configurations.</td>
<td>Virtual machines are created using the same image.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>It comes with 3 fault domains and 5 update domains.</td>
<td>It comes with 5 fault domains and 5 update domains.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>It is possible to add a virtual machine in the availability set only during its creation.</td>
<td>Scale set allows to increase or decrease the number of virtual machines depending on the demand.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Availability sets are ideal to use when the workload requirements are predefined.</td>
<td>Scale sets are ideal for handling unknown workloads since they support auto-scaling.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h4><strong>32. What are the steps for connecting to an Azure database from SQL Management Studio?</strong></h4>
Here are the steps to connect to an Azure database from SQL Management Studio:
<ul>
 	<li>Start the SQL Server Management Studio.</li>
 	<li>If you are starting the SQL Server Management Studio for the first time, it will show you a dialog box that prompts you to “Connect to Server.” If the dialog box doesn’t appear, you can access the “Connect to Server” option by navigating to Object Explorer→Connect→ Database Engine.</li>
 	<li>Once you open the Connect to Server window, you need to provide the information about the Azure server that you want to connect to. The information fields include Server Type, Server Name, Authentication, Login ID, and Password.</li>
 	<li>Once you enter all the required information, you simply need to click the “Connect button” and the SQL Management Studio will connect with the specified Azure database.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>33. What is Azure App Service?</strong></h4>
Azure App Service is a dedicated HTTP-based service that specifically intends to host web applications, back-end code of mobile apps, and REST APIs. It offers Windows and Linux-based environments for apps to run and scale with ease.

App Service combines the best of Azure features that ensure optimal performance of applications, such as auto-scaling, load balancing, and automated management.
<h4><strong>34. Explain the types of data services offered by Azure Storage.</strong></h4>
Azure Storage offers various data services that are as follows:
<ul>
 	<li><b>Blobs: </b>The Azure Blob Storage service allows users to store text and binary data. It can integrate with Data Lake Storage Gen2 to enable big data analytics.</li>
 	<li><b>Queues: </b>It acts as a message queue system that facilitates messaging between the different components of an application. Also, it helps to develop applications having large workloads.</li>
 	<li><b>Files: </b>The Azure Files service enables file sharing by using the Server Message Block (SMB) protocol for both on-premises and cloud deployments.</li>
 	<li><b>Tables: </b>It is a NoSQL store for structured data that does not require a schema.</li>
 	<li><b>Disks: </b>Azure Disks is a storage service that provides block-level storage volumes exclusively for Azure virtual machines (VMs).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>35. How to create a virtual machine with Azure CLI?</strong></h4>
You simply need to open the Azure CLI and run the following command to create a virtual machine:
<pre>az vm create \
    --resource-group sampleResourceGroup \
    --name testVM \
    --image Win2019Datacenter \
    --admin-username testuser
    --admin-password samplePASSWORD@123</pre>
<h4><strong>36. What are the differences between Azure Table Storage and Azure SQL Table?</strong></h4>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><b>Azure Table Storage</b></td>
<td><b>Azure SQL Table</b></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>It is an Azure service for storing NoSQL data.</td>
<td>It is an Azure service for storing data that follows a relational structure.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The data schema is not required.</td>
<td>Data gets stored in accordance with a data schema.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Data is generally stored in the form of key-value pairs.</td>
<td>Data is stored as combinations of rows and columns in the SQL table.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>No relationship between the tables.</td>
<td>There are relationships between the tables that are defined using foreign keys.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h4><strong>37. List all the power states of a virtual machine in Azure.</strong></h4>
There are six power states of a virtual machine in Azure:
<ol>
 	<li>Starting</li>
 	<li>Stopping</li>
 	<li>Running</li>
 	<li>Deallocating</li>
 	<li>Stopped</li>
 	<li>Deallocated</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>38. What are the steps to create a resource group in Azure?</strong></h4>
The following are the steps required for creating a resource group:
<ul>
 	<li>Login to Azure account.</li>
 	<li>Access the “Resource groups” from the main menu located on the upper left side of the screen.</li>
 	<li>Click on the ‘Add’ option.</li>
 	<li>Provide the details required for creating the new resource group.</li>
 	<li>Click on “Review + create”.</li>
 	<li>After the validation completes, click “Create.”</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>39. Describe the role of Text Analytics API in Azure.</strong></h4>
The Text Analytics API offered by Azure is a range of web services that are suitable for analyzing unstructured data purposes including key-phrase and entity extraction and sentiment analysis.

The best thing about these web services is that they are created using high-performance machine learning algorithms. Also, the Text Analytics API makes use of the natural language processing (NLP) technology to make meaningful predictions.
<h4><strong>40. What are application partitions?</strong></h4>
In general, application patterns are simply directory partitions that are replicated to domain controllers. Also, application patterns are a part of the Azure Active Directory system.

Application patterns intend to limit the replication traffic by allowing you to replicate their attributes as well as the value to any domain controller. Unlike domain partitions, application partitions can focus only on a single domain area, which results in them being redundant and highly available.
<h2><strong>To Sum it Up</strong></h2>
The demand for professionals who can work with Microsoft Azure is increasing gradually. If you want to crack your upcoming Azure interview, you definitely need to prepare yourself in the best possible way.

The Azure interview questions and answers mentioned above can help you to polish your knowledge and give you a good idea about what to expect during the interview.

Also, we have divided the Azure interview questions based on the complexity of the topics that they cover. Thus, it’s important for you to go through all the questions to improve your knowledge of Azure.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>22512</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2022-03-08 04:59:57]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2022-03-08 04:59:57]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:post_modified><![CDATA[2022-03-08 04:59:57]]></wp:post_modified>
		<wp:post_modified_gmt><![CDATA[2022-03-08 04:59:57]]></wp:post_modified_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[top-azure-interview-questions-and-answers]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
										<category domain="category" nicename="azure"><![CDATA[Azure]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="azure"><![CDATA[Azure]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="azure-interview-questions"><![CDATA[Azure Interview Questions]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="interview-questions"><![CDATA[Interview Questions]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="interview-questions"><![CDATA[Interview Questions]]></category>
						<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_pingme]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_encloseme]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_yoast_wpseo_focuskw]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[Azure Interview Questions]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_yoast_wpseo_title]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[40 Top Azure Interview Questions and Answers in 2022 [Recommended]]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_yoast_wpseo_metadesc]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[Preparing for an upcoming interview for the Azure professional role? Find the top Azure interview questions and answers that you need to know.]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_yoast_wpseo_linkdex]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[65]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_yoast_wpseo_content_score]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[30]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_yoast_wpseo_estimated-reading-time-minutes]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[18]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_yoast_wpseo_primary_category]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2753]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							</item>
				</channel>
</rss>
	